[ boy ] It 's gone now , Mummy .
What 's gone ?
The whistle whistling .
What whistling ?
Okay . You go to sleep now .
Shh .
Pass . Pass .
Do you know what , I can 't remember the last time we went for a trek over the tarn .
We should go .
Gordon could look after Owen .
Mmm .
[ indistinct screams ]
[ child screaming ]
[ horse whinnying ]
Richard , where 's Owen ?
[ crying ]
[ horse cries in pain ]
Owen , son , what 's happened ?
What 's happened ?
Finish your breakfast .
[ radio chatter ]
[ Juliette ] Yes , of course .
No , we 'll both be there .
Thank you so much . Thank you .
Well , Doctor Ellis had already heard about the fair .
And he 's referred us to a clinic in Wakefield .
Right .
And they 're very good , apparently .
Well ...
Okay .
I 've gotta go .
See you later , son .
[ radio chatter ]
What happened yesterday , lovely ?
Yesterday ?
At the fair .
I played football .
But is anything on your mind ?
You can always tell me if something 's troubling you .
[ chicken calls ]
Go on . Go on , down you get .
It 's just in here .
- Okay ? - Come this way .
We 've all the latest action figures in there .
It 's just down here .
Yes , it 's where Richard grew up . It 's his parents ' old place .
And you were in central Leeds before that ?
Do you think that has something to do with it ?
Well , sometimes a big change in their environment could , yeah .
We moved over two years ago .
Owen doesn 't really remember , I don 't think .
We thought the space and the fresh air would be good for ...
That 's good for everyone .
So ...
please can you tell us what you plan to do for Owen .
Well , we need to ascertain whether Owen 's aggression will return
by trying to work out what the trigger is .
- Owen 's not aggressive . - Richard .
He 's been in a couple of scraps at school ,
but he were just defending himself .
Did he start displaying this behavior at school ?
Yes .
But he hasn 't given you any other cause for concern
apart from this one incident ?
No , he 's never done anything this bad .
I see .
I think there 's a voice ...
Or something inside his head .
What makes you say that ?
He said that someone called Jack Grey
is whistling to him .
When did he say that ?
The other day when he was asleep .
Where do you think he got that name from ?
Oh , I know .
Our neighbors , Gordon , he comes round , he looks after him . Likes to tell him stories .
Look , this voice ...
it provokes him ,
to do things that he knows he shouldn 't do .
Let 's try to find out how this voice comes to him .
Whether it 's external or if it 's in his mind .
Have you seen this type of thing before ?
Let me have a look at him . We 've had some success here with EEG testing .
It 's a brain scan .
Right .
Good lad . We 'll be done in a minute .
- [ whimpers ] - [ machine whirrs ]
It 's all right .
Nearly there .
Come on , lovely , it 's okay .
There you go . Hold him .
Yeah , try not to move , Owen . Owen . That 's it , stay there .
I don 't want Gordon here .
Don 't want him coming round any more filling
Owen 's head full of magic .
This is exactly what I wanted to avoid moving back here .
So who is this Jack Grey ?
[ turns water off ]
No-one .
- Come on . - Come on what ? Just a wood sprite
my dad made up . Him and Gordon used to
try and scare me with it when I was a kid .
What did they do ?
Don 't matter . It were pure idiocy .
It matters to some extent because Owen thinks he 's whistling to him .
Yeah , well , that 's why Gordon 's banned from the house .
Gets a kick out of tormenting children , that man .
It 's the last thing Owen needs right now .
These were some of her belongings buried with her .
What do you think they tell us ?
That 's really interesting craftsmanship there .
Yeah , it shows that the people liked to look good even then .
Well , yes , that 's right .
It suggests that the Jutish people weren 't just rolling around in the mud ,
you know , but that they cared about these things . They cared about themselves .
And that they were relatively healthy people .
Right .
Would 've thought you might have got yourself a haircut , Willoughby .
Ready , Jeremy ?
Four minutes is completely unnecessary .
You can make a perfectly good cup of tea in 30 seconds .
He acts like the introduction of modern analysis is my fault .
Well , he 's just old guard .
Oh , you know
I 'll buy him a metal detector for his retirement .
Well , you know , I did hear him say that he 's got a few years left in him .
Jesus .
But if he does hang up his chalk next summer , you should maybe
think about your research activity before putting yourself forward .
[ clears throat ]
[ humming [
Mind your step .
People have ...
forgotten about it , but somewhere in this field
should be the roots of an old oak tree .
I know .
- Oh , how do you know ? - Gordon told me .
Oh , yeah . Well ,
do you know why the tree was important ?
People used it as a meeting place .
That 's right .
They did .
Used to meet there for different reasons .
To sell animals , to , er
well , to deal with issues in the village ,
or to judge folks if they were naughty .
You mean to hang people ?
I might do .
Your granddaddy bought this land , you know ...
because he was interested in all the stories it had to tell .
Gordon says the oak tree 's spirit
was like a doorway into other worlds .
Well , that 's not true . Gordon 's full of superstitions .
Silly ideas people made up before we understood how things really worked .
This place is beautiful as it is , without superstitions .
We 've moved on from that . All right ?
What happened to the tree ?
Well , it was a long , long time ago .
It was probably removed to make way for farming , I 'd guess .
We should try to find where the roots are , Daddy .
You know what , son , that 's a good idea .
We will . I promise .
I 'll start digging .
But we need to get that barn fixed for your mother first .
Has mummy decided if she wants sheep or goats ?
Goats , I think .
Gordon .
The chickens will love this .
Oh , you shouldn 't have .
That face sings a sad song . What 's mitherin ' you ?
Gordon , you don 't understand .
He doesn 't remember what he 's done afterwards .
Well , maybe he don 't want to remember .
Can only imagine how he 's been goaded at school , and then at fair .
You know what kids are like , vicious buggers .
They are . I 'll tell you that .
I can 't speak to Richard about it . He 's convinced that everything 's fine with Owen .
He has a lot of compassion for your son .
Making up for things .
I don 't speak ill of dead , but Richard and his dad
didn 't see eye to eye from start .
I know he was very hard on him .
He never speaks about Neil .
It 's ancient news .
Point is , Richard 's heart is in right place .
What have you found ?
Here , Owen . See this ? It 's a crinoid .
Probably over 300 million years old that .
What else can we find ?
Look at this one , Daddy . Look how smooth it is .
Good lad . It is .
And do you know why it 's smooth ? Because the water pressure has made it so .
- I got a big one . - Go on , lob it .
Can you skim it ?
What 's a skim ?
It 's obvious he wasn 't himself at the fair .
If people could have seen him today , they 'd change their minds .
This is his normal state .
They 're too quick to judge .
Are you all right ?
You 're warm .
It 's gonna be okay .
I 'm gonna sort the mess out in the study this weekend .
Might check out my dad 's old stuff .
And I 'll start work on that barn for you .
[ birds chirping
[ rooster crowing ]
[ chatter ]
Sorry I 'm late .
I know he 's not necessarily in the area
analysis ...
Owen ? Owen .
What 's happened ? Owen .
Owen ? Owen !
Owen , breathe . Come on .
Come on . Owen , breathe .
Owen , no ...
The farmhouse at the end of Stythwaite Lane .
- Please hurry . - No !
Come on , then . Come on . It 's all right .
I 've got you .
It 's okay . It 's okay . Come on .
I 'm here to see my son . Owen Willoughby .
Down here ?
Jules ?
Jules !
Hey , I 'm here .
[ sobs ]
Where is he ?
Hi , Richard .
- You all right with your bag ? - Yeah . Thanks , I 've got it .
- Come on in . - Thanks .
How are you both ?
Yeah , good . We 're fine .
Jules about ?
Yeah .
Let me get her .
Jules ?
I 'll not be a sec .
[ door opens ]
Jules ?
Mmm .
Harrie 's here .
Already ?
It 's one o 'clock .
Come on .
Right , she 'll be down .
Have you found any buried treasure out there yet ?
Not today .
Well , it 's good you 're working .
Aye .
Were the roads okay ?
Yeah . Had to take it easy once I got off the A1 .
Oh , yeah . How 's Tommy ?
Usual self .
Jules .
- You 're skin and bones . - Don 't start doing your mom impression .
- Are you eating properly ? - I 'm fine .
What ?
I don 't know why you 'd wanna come here .
See my sister . Is that so ridiculous ?
I made you this .
It 's lime and coconut . It 's a bit dry . Sorry .
I cooked it in a cake tin . I should have baked it like a loaf , but it 'll taste fine .
Mum and Benji are a bit worried .
If they found out I was allowed here before them , they 'd have a fit .
Mom can 't bear it here .
- That is not true . - Yes , it is .
She couldn 't wait to leave after the wake .
And all they do is fuss anyway .
So , Rosencrantz ...
I never understood the appeal of Michael Caine .
He 's such a mummy 's boy .
Gene Hackman though , I 'd nurture his seed .
I 've never heard anyone say they fancy Gene Hackman .
[ man on TV ] Who comes here ?
Mommy .
[ eerie whistling ]
[ birds calling ]
Where 's Juliette ?
In her bedroom .
What 's going on ?
Don 't touch his stuff .
What does your sister think she 's doing ?
I asked her to .
We don 't need her here . She 's a fucking busybody .
Richard ...
how else are we gonna sort out his room ?
You can 't just erase it all .
No .
Let 's not fight .
- I knew you weren 't happy with Owen . - Don 't .
I did .
But all we had to do was love him ...
without all the judgement .
You think I was blind ...
hmm , to his problems .
All I ever did was try and show him love and affection .
It might have helped if you 'd acknowledged what was going on a little bit more .
Oh , yeah .
Where were you when he was having the attack ?
I 'm asking .
[ vomits ]
Jules ?
What 's going on ?
Your coat .
You 'll freeze to death .
Gordon ?
Oh , morning , blossom .
We were just passing and I really wanted you to meet Mrs. Forde .
8Well , he said you knew I was coming .
Jules .
Oh , this is my sister Harrie .
This is my neighbor , Gordon . And Mrs. Forde .
Jules , why don 't they come inside ?
Well , that might not be a good idea . I 'm not in lad 's good books .
- Mrs . Forde might though . - Well ...
only if it 's not too much trouble .
Can we get you anything ?
Oh , no .
Gordon 's a big fan of yours .
- Why is that ? - Well , I ...
like to help people .
I teach yoga , meditation , you know , that sort of thing .
- Gordon tells me you meditate ? - Not for a while .
Why not ?
Well ...
we could try together ...
if you 'd like , all of us ?
Just ...
a simple chant ?
Help readdress the balance .
What do you think ?
Give it a try . No harm .
Yeah ?
Let 's , um , let 's create a peaceful place .
Would you get the curtains ?
Let 's not be foemen indefinitely .
You know , we 've all made mistakes in life , some more than others .
But I swear ...
I treated Owen as if he were my own .
That 's why you scared him into having night terrors .
In what way ?
Filling his head with stories of Jack Grey .
- Hey , I never mentioned that to him . - Well , I certainly didn 't .
Well , anyone could have done .
- Kids at school . - It was my dad 's delusion .
You and him were the only ones that told me that story .
Well , I regret how I acted with thee when thee were young .
And your dad were wrong to do what he did to thee . And I told him .
Look , Gordon if Jules wants to visit you ,
then that 's up to her , but I 'm fine here . All right ?
So be it , lad .
But contempt for those around you is only a self-fulfilling prophecy .
Oh , uh yeah , " Thank you . "
Okay .
Let 's take a breath .
[ inhales ]
Om Vajrapani Hum .
Close your eyes ...
and keep the light in your mind .
[ inhales ]
Om Vajrapani ...
No , I can 't .
It 's okay , love .
If any negative thoughts enter ...
just let them , so that then they can pass on .
Let 's expel our demons .
You will feel so much better .
I promise you . Let 's try .
Only if you want to .
Let 's exchange this energy we 're feeling for anew .
[ inhales ]
Om Vajrapani Hum . ..
[ exhales and inhales ]
Let it out . [ exhales ]
[ inhales ]
I 'm sorry .
It 's okay .
[ sobs ]
I 'm a disgrace .
[ Mrs. Forde ] He forgives you .
- We all forgive you . - No .
Forgive yourself .
Tell your son ...
he can go now .
Let him pass on .
Try , try to just say it once .
Go ...
my love .
Good .
Om Vajrapani Hum . ..
Let him free ...
with your exhale .
[ chanting ]
It 's fine .
- It 's okay . - Oh my God .
It 's okay .
The Dandelion has bud .
[ panting ]
[ screams ]
No , don 't be afraid ! It 's okay .
Take it easy .
He has , er ...
moved on now .
He has , I promise you .
Gordon 's waiting outside .
A bloom of spring is on the way .
Ta-ra , love .
[ Richard ] Jules ?
Harrie ?
You all right ? What 's ...
what 's been going on in here ?
- Was it Gordon ? What 's he done ? - It 's not Gordon .
What then ? Who was that with him ?
Mrs. Forde .
Mrs. Forde ?
She performed a show of some sort .
She came ...
She came to help release Owen .
What ?
All right .
Go on . Go back to sticking your head in the fucking mud !
Go on then , leave us !
Don 't . Don 't .
[ sighs ]
You play off scratch ?
Well , I haven 't been a member of a club for 20 years now .
Well , of course . But still ...
Willoughby .
Um , yeah , I 'm just here to collect some stuff .
- How are you ? - Fine .
Good . Steven tells me you 're getting your hands dirty ,
which is encouraging .
Have the board discussed my return date yet ?
We 're going to assess it over the summer .
We felt like you needed a full sabbatical year .
You deserve the time off for yourself ...
and your wife . Anyway ...
- good to see you . - Yeah .
You 're chums now ?
No , we were just , um ...
What 's going on ?
There 's something I wanted your take on .
Okay .
Um ...
it 's a ...
a rabbit , or a hare .
There 's some ...
fungus starting to attack ...
just here , but , um ...
I mean , what am I supposed to be looking for ?
Sorry about this .
It 's okay .
[ door closes ]
[ sighs ]
Did I tell you Tommy drank all my Pomerol ?
Didn 't even say anything .
Turned my back and he 'd had the whole lot .
Is this paint even working ?
It 's rubbish . Look , I put two coats up here and I can still see the stains .
Had one glass of my birthday gift .
Stupid man .
Stupid , stupid man .
[ sighs ]
Stupid man .
[ eerie music playing ]
[ chopping ]
Harrie made curry .
Richard , come on .
- Please , I 'm sorry . - Okay .
Please come back with me .
The sea air might do us some good .
Yeah , maybe .
I 'm starting to feel a bit landlocked here .
I think that 's Yellow Star .
- Jules , what do you think ? - I 've never seen that here .
Come on .
Bit of time away might help you both .
Go on then .
Richard ...
can we talk ?
No !
I thought you 'd gone out .
Just for a walk . What 's going on in there ?
Nothing .
- Let me in . - Please . No , wait .
- What is going on in here ? - Be quiet !
Please .
Needed my help .
What was wrong with it ?
I don 't know .
Well , it seems okay now .
Yeah , you think ?
Yeah .
We have to let him go .
He wouldn 't survive in here . He needs to be outside . And look , he 's ...
- They 're nervous creatures . - I know , I know that .
He is lovely though .
Yeah , right then . Come on .
Just mind out , please . Mind out , Harrie , go on .
What 's this for ?
This should hold him .
- Hold who ? - No-one .
Jules ?
Could you keep Corey away for a bit .
Um ...
What are you talking about ?
It 's just house stuff .
We need something to prop this open .
Come on , then .
It 's okay .
It 's all right .
Come on , little one .
It 's okay .
What 's this ?
Come on .
Richard , grab , grab it .
[ growling ]
- Open the box . Open it . - Okay .
Sorry .
Jesus !
Richard , just forget the blanket .
- Christ ! - Sorry , sorry . I 'm sorry , darling .
[ growling ]
Right , get the door .
Okay .
What is going on in there ?
What is it ?
Watch your step .
Jules ...
- what have you got in there ? - Nothing , Harrie .
Richard 's just been looking after it .
He 's all right .
Here .
- Fuckin ' hell . - Oh , come on .
What do you think ?
Here ?
Yes .
Come on , mate . Steady .
Go on , it 's okay .
Go on now .
Go on .
No , no , shoo .
Go on . Shoo .
Go on .
Hey , shoo . Go on .
That 's it .
[ tense music playing ]
[ melancholy music playing ]
What 's going on ?
Richard ?
You know , when I was Owen 's age ...
Mmm-hmm .
My dad used to strip me down to my underpants ...
and , er , tape my mouth up ...
Make me stand out in the field ...
For hours , freezing .
I never knew he did anything like that .
My fingers turned blue .
He wanted me to disappear .
To disappear ?
Why ?
[ sniffs ]
Some sick idea of his .
He was disturbed , that man .
I 'm sorry .
I never knew .
Why didn 't you say ?
I didn 't want it to get in the way or noth ...
When you mentioned moving here , I thought ...
you know ...
forget him .
I wanted to give ...
my son the life that I wish I 'd had here .
I don 't really know what 's happening anymore .
What do you mean ?
- It 's okay . - [ sobbing ]
Sshh , it 's okay .
[ sobs ]
[ eerie whistling ]
My shoulder doesn 't hurt anymore .
[ footsteps ]
Just taking Corey out .
In return for the Triquetra sacrifice ...
It 's some sort of local folklore .
- You shouldn 't be in here . - This says followers gathered at Starve Acre .
Three of them died .
A child , woman and a man .
They were sacrificed for the Dandelion to bud .
It 's all the same as Mrs. Forde 's jargon .
And Richard 's dad was writing about it , too .
The gods are just , the gods are fair ,
they let Jack free and into our care .
The price we pay is one , two , three ,
To let joy pour from the Whistling Tree .
Kept this quiet .
It 's still covered in bark .
That 's the density of the soil .
No , no , it 's deliberate .
The villagers cut it down .
Why bury it ?
Well , if my dad 's writing is anything to go on ...
they were sealing short access to the , er ...
" womb of nature . "
The Pagan 's entrance to the spirit world .
That 's a wild notion for 17th century England .
Um , I 'm sorry about my visit to work . I were ...
just , er , morbid curiosity got the better of me .
No , no worries .
Let 's get this sorted .
There 's a whole section about Neil trying to release the same spirit .
He documents all these things he did to Richard .
It 's fucking weird , Jules .
And who is this Dandelion Jack ?
I mean , have you ever heard of him ?
No .
I , I don 't quite understand .
How is the trunk so well-preserved ?
You 've hit the jackpot here , Richard , come on , the Faculty should be funding this .
.Who 's that ?
Oh , no !
Hang on .
Richard .
What 's happened ?
It went for him . It attacked Corey .
What did ?
He 's okay , because I blocked it . I blocked it .
Jesus , you need stitches .
Come on . Let 's go in . You 're all right .
Jesus Christ .
[ sobs ]
It was that fucking thing .
Hey , Jules .
Don 't .
It 's just had Harrie 's arm .
2It 's all right .
Juliette !
Shh .
It 's all right .
Jules .
Look what it 's done .
It 's ripped open my arm .
Why would he do that ?
[ Harrie ] Richard .
He doesn 't seem to need anything .
- Everything all right ? - Oh , yeah , yeah .
Looks like an attempt to hide evidence .
Several hangings . At least five or six , all the way down .
I mean , I 've never seen anything like this before .
The condition it 's in is just , it 's just mind-boggling .
Sweet joy that enchants .
What is it , my darling ?
[ Steven ] I am here for him !
I am here for him !
No !
No .
[ eerie whistling ]
Look ...
even under here ...
the soil ...
the way it 's , the way it 's mummified the oak ...
and preserved all the bark , it 's ...
It 's like it 's , it 's like it 's just been buried .
Fuck 's sake .
You won 't have much luck with that , love .
Yeah , I noticed .
You can come back and use my phone if you like .
No , thank you , Gordon , I 've gotta get going .
What 's happened to arm ?
I fell ...
that 's all .
You going back to house ?
Hey , look .
We 're as surprised as you are .
It were Richard 's old man who tried to summon The Dandelion .
Aye .
He even attempted to offer up his own son as first ransom .
But Jack weren 't interested . It don 't work like that .
Richard ? Are you okay ?
Are you all right , pal ?
Okay , just try and breathe , yeah . Just ...
[ Gordon ] It 's Jack who chooses .
And only a son who is much beloved by his father would do .
And Richard weren 't , you see . But Owen was .
That 's how it works .
And now Richard 's uncovered the entrance , the ransom can be settled .
I need to get going .
Where you headed , love ?
Look , you should be happy Jack has chosen your sister .
He 's come to give her another chance .
[ groaning ]
I 'm here .
Jules ?
Hey , Jules !
I 'll get help , okay .
Jules !
Why deny it ? We gave him physical form .
We did .
No-one else could .
Your father wasn 't able to .
When Owen had the asthma attack ...
I didn 't freeze up .
I had a moment of clarity that we 'd be better off without him .
And that was thanks to Jack .
He knows .
No .
Jack knows .
We 'll look after him .
Let him ...
pour joy over sorrow .
Stay here , okay , angel .
Jules ?
No , Harrie , don 't .
Don 't come in .
Don 't .
Come on .
Let 's get him towel .
He wants you .
Come .
I love you .
Come on .
Take it .
Sorry , Harrie .
Come on .
Into the womb of nature ,
Accept these tokens of affection .
Harrie , you can come in .
Come .
He wants to play with you .
Go on .
♪ It hails , it rains , it snows , it blows ♪
♪ And I am wet through all me clothes ♪
♪ So my prithee love let me in ♪
♪ To let you in that cannot be ♪
♪ There 's nobody in this house but me ♪
♪ So I dare not let you in ♪
♪ Me dad and mom , they 're fast asleep ♪
♪ Me brother is up , he 's with the sheep ♪
♪ So I dare not let thee in ♪
♪ We turned him round in wither to go ♪
♪ The storm were dark ♪
♪ And the rain did blow ♪
♪ She called him back again ♪
♪ And the wind did blow ♪